hey everyone its Melanie welcome back to
my channel today's video we are gonna
make your first quilts super excited
about this little series where I think
we're gonna do four videos but we'll see
this will be video number one and we are
gonna make your first quilt together
alright so this is kind of what it looks
like patchwork made with a charm pack
okay so we're gonna take one of those
daunting steps right out of your first
quilt and use a pre-cut that will allow
us to just get right to sewing so that's
what we're gonna do for this first video
we're gonna get this top sewn together
your first quilt it's gonna be super fun
and then I'm gonna show you how to baste
it and quilt it and bind it and all that
good stuff but I'm gonna walk you
through really slow so this is gonna be
a series meant for those of you that
have always wanted to learn how to make
a quilt and so this is gonna be like
absolute beginner I'm gonna go super
super slow I also wanted to tell you
guys about my five days to better
quilting free mini class so this is a
little mini class I've offered for a
long time but in case you haven't seen
it it's called five days to better
quilting so that's the number five days
quilting calm and I've had this
available for awhile I just went back in
and made sure that all the videos are
working and all the emails that look
good
it has so much information and I still
regularly get emails from people letting
me know how much they enjoyed the little
class and and how much they learned from
it so if you're a beginner quilter that
is also a great resource for you guys I
have lots of like the list of good
fabric manufacturers and tools that you
might want to invest in and all kinds of
things so definitely check that out
again five the number five days quilting
calm but let's jump right in I've got a
nice beginner tutorial for you let's
make your first quilt hey everyone so
today's video is going to be how to make
your very first quilts so I'm gonna walk
you through all the steps and my biggest
recommendation when you're making your
very first quilt is to start with the
charm pack so we are going to be making
a basic patchwork small quilts nothing
too unmanageable so I want you to find a
charm pack and charm packs our five inch
squares and they're already pre-cut for
you in the entire line of fabric so
there's lots of them to choose from I'm
gonna actually be using this one from
the fabric line
Caturday that's what it's gonna look
like but any other charm pack that you
would like to use pick one out they
should have about 42 pieces in there
they're all about the same size so find
one of these and then we will head over
to the sewing machine so actually before
we head to the sewing machine we want to
do our layout so we want to take this
apart and find a dining table a floor a
clean surface of some of some kind to
lay out your fabric so play around with
your layout and as long as you have 42
squares in your charm pack I want you to
arrange it so that you have six squares
across and seven squares going down so
go ahead and get your layout figured out
and then we're gonna organize everything
and head over to the sewing machine the
great thing about the charm packs is
that they're pre-cut for you so that
takes a whole step out so when you're
very first getting into quilting it's a
great start okay so here is my layout I
just did this on the floor of my sewing
room so you don't need anything super
fancy now I'm gonna show you how to
organize your stacks of fabric that way
you can take everything over to the
sewing machine and you won't have to
keep getting up and down the first thing
that you want to do though is take a
picture because inevitably my cat comes
along and knocks over a stack or
something happens and this way you'll
just have a back-up plan so that you can
refer to it in case you need to this
also helps you sort of determine if you
want to change anything in your
placement for example you know I'm okay
with this but this is a little bit of a
solid block down here I maybe would want
them to move some things around so you
can kind of check it out that way all
right so this is how I like to organize
my stacks and if you find a different
way of doing it that works better for
you feel free to do that instead so what
I like to do is take two columns at a
time so I place right sides together
so right side on top of the right side
and then I stack from the top going down
so then I will know that I need to sew
along this right edge and that this is
the top fabric of columns 1 & 2 so then
what I'll do is I'll go and do the same
thing on the other 4 columns and I'll
stack them and label them that way we
can head to the sewing machine and not
have to worry about getting things
misplace we don't have to get up and
down everything is there we could just
zoom through and get everything sewn
alright now here we go we've got our
three stocks I labeled them call them 1
& 2 3 & 4 5 & 6 so we're gonna put 3 4 5
& 6 aside for now and here's column 1 &
2 now I'm going to teach you a technique
called chain piecing and this is a
lifesaver when it comes to quilting and
it makes it go really fast very
efficient you don't use up too much
thread so it's great you can use a
thread that is whatever you like I use
Artefill and I like a kind of soft dove
gray like this especially when I'm using
lots of different colors from my fabric
line so if you're using all very light
colors you can use white or all very
dark colors just something that
coordinates with everything so the way
chain piecing works is you're gonna grab
your first two pieces of fabric remember
everything is should be the right
direction we know we need to sew down
the right side we are gonna line up our
edges and we're gonna measure our
quarter inch seam so everything with
quilting is quarter-inch seam allowance
and we're gonna measure that from the
edge of our fabric so if you have a pink
edge this little zigzag edge is called a
pink edge and if you have that we're
gonna measure that quarter inch from the
outside of that not from the inside of
that zigzag so I'm gonna place this
underneath my presser foot don't worry I
will get a close
up and I'm going to use a piecing foot
but many of you as a beginner quilter
may not have a piecing foot for your
sewing machine and a piecing foot just
means it's already a perfect
quarter-inch so I'm going to show you
how to use your plate that comes on your
sewing machine so right down here on
this plate that says one - fourths right
there you'll see it on your machine and
I'm going to line up my edges with that
line so there's no need to backstitch
with piecing quilting and then we will
sew that through now don't cut your
threads we're just gonna press on that
presser foot and get a few extra
stitches and then we're gonna grab the
next two fabrics from our pile line up
those edges lift up that presser foot
and then we are gonna continue sewing
now occasionally pre cuts are not cut
perfectly and so that's okay we are
going to kind of watch out for that in
our next step but if you see some edges
that aren't quite lining up don't stress
out
and you're gonna just keep doing this
chain piecing with all of your fabrics
until you get to the end of your two
columns and I'll meet you there all
right I've just finished my last one now
we can lift up our presser foot take it
off the machine and use your thread
cutter or whatever you have to cut that
thread so now I have one of these little
guys that helps me cut everything but
just regular old scissors will work just
fine
so I'm gonna go through and just
remember that you need to keep the last
one you did is one that goes on the
bottom because the top the first fabric
you've fed through the machine was from
the top of the quilts so as we go down
that way we can stay nice and organized
and you always know that the seam is on
the right hand side in case you got
confused so here is my stock and I'm
gonna put my label back on there just in
case and you know sometimes I even like
to pin it cuz my little cat Jack he's a
little feisty one sometimes so I'm gonna
put this aside and now I'm gonna follow
that exact same method for the remaining
stacks of fabric that I have and of
course if you wanted to use to charm
packs or three charm packs and make a
nice big quilt totally fine I'm just
encouraging you to keep it small for
your beginning of quilting dirty so go
ahead and finish the row three and four
or column three and four excuse me and
column five and six and then we will get
to our rows all right so now we have all
three piles done and ready to go and now
we can start putting our rows together
and the cool thing about this method is
that you don't even need to get up from
your sewing machine we can just stay put
right here or if you hear that piano in
the background my son is practicing so
we have the top stack okay so here's our
top stack we're gonna move that over
here and we have our next one and then
we have our third okay so while we're
sitting here just go ahead and create
these rows so I'm gonna leave the third
one here I'm gonna place my right sides
together
from the first set and the second set
and then we will send this through the
machine
and I'm going to go ahead and cut that
one I'm gonna open it back up and then
I'm going to add the set from the third
stack to the end right sides together
line up those edges and send that
through the machine
so now we've got call row one not column
one what row one complete so what I do
is I just set this aside I my work table
is right behind me
so I put this on my work table and that
is the top one from the quilt right so
then and we're gonna work our way down
so then the top of that stack that I'm
making of all the rows will be from the
bottom of the quilt so all that to say
just keep track of which is the top one
which is the bottom one and if you need
to refer to your photo totally fine so
now I'll take the next one's so now so
all of these together and keep doing
that until you have all seven of your
rows complete alright so here we have
all of our rows now are complete with
our bottom row here on the top so just
keep track of that so what we need to do
now is we're gonna put our rows together
so we're gonna have the bottom row here
and then we needed the next row and then
I'm just gonna stack the rest of these
up and out of the way okay so we want
all of the seams from the bottom row
going in one direction budget whether
that's the left or the right doesn't
matter you can do this at the ironing
board if that helps you but I want to
show you how you know I feel like as a
beginner there's so many steps to
quilting so I'm trying to minimize the
steps and and have you feel confident
about what you're doing so all of the
seams need to be facing let's say to the
left okay so that means this seam
underneath where our connections are
they need to be to the left and so you
can just do a little finger press just
kind of gently run your fingers along
those seams and I want to just kind of
teach you this concept this is called
nesting your seams and then what happens
is the next row up here all of these are
going to be facing to the right okay so
I'm going to
finger press these as well to the right
and what that does when the bottom is to
the left and the top of to the right you
have the seams lock into place when you
sew them together and that makes it so
that you get those nice perfect corners
those perfect little patchwork corners
okay
so we did a little finger press you can
do this with the ironing board if you
want but I don't I just sit at my
machine and do it our seams going
opposite directions and that's good we
like that because that seam will lock
that seam will lock into place and
you'll get that nice perfect corner so
what I recommend for beginners is pin
all of these intersections until you get
the hang of it so I've got those seams
nice and locked together so I'm gonna
add a pin then I'm gonna go down and
same thing I'm gonna kind of wiggle you
can kind of wiggle it in your fingers
and feel that seemed like there but
right up next to each other will slide a
little pin in there and then go to the
next one so now that that's done we can
send this through the sewing machine
[Music]
when you get close to the seam going
through the needle take your PIN out and
hold your fingers right where it was and
slowly send it through don't run over
those pins with your sewing machine
don't want anybody sending a broken
needle into their eyeball sometimes as
you run it through the underneath seam
kind of flips back toward yourself so
just make sure everything's laying flat
all right let's see how we did so that's
how you want your points to look that is
what nesting the seam does helps you get
those nice corners and if you did not
get that nice corner that is okay please
do not rip it out as long as your stitch
is good and your fabric is connecting
keep going because there's nothing more
so to begin are gonna have feeling
discouraged and having to rip all your
stuff out no one will notice in the end
I promise so now what you'll do is same
idea so if all of these from the top row
the seams are facing to the right so
that means our next row the seams are
gonna feed the opposite direction so we
can lock in those seams together and
nest them so make sure we get those nice
points and that's all there is to it to
continue putting your entire quilt top
together so once your quilt top is sewn
all completely sewn I'll meet you at the
ironing board and that is when we're
gonna give this a nice good press
alright so here's our little cool top
ready to be pressed I've got my iron on
now what we're gonna do we're gonna flip
it over to the back and we're gonna give
it a nice good press the two things
there's two ways of doing this you can
iron your seam open which basically
would mean to split this open like so
and you would iron along there I don't
think it's necessary when we just have
these standard seams when you get some
more complicated things like stars where
you have a lot of fabric kind of bulking
up these seams then I think that's a
great way of doing it but I'm gonna do
it to one side it's also a little faster
than ironing it open but there is two
ways of doing it so I do want you to be
aware of that so what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna take my iron and I'm gonna
press it down and I'm gonna press down
all of these themes as well and when you
press and quilting you want to press and
lift press and lift we don't want to run
the iron along the fabric and distort
anything
and we also don't want to use steam so a
dry iron is usually better a little
steam is okay if you need it if it's
super wrinkled so I'm going to press the
seam down and I'm gonna do that for all
those row seams and as I'm moving it
along I'm lifting it slightly hold it in
place
lift slightly I'm lifting it up and then
I'm pressing it back down that way we'll
have nice pressed seams and we can go to
our next step
but once you do that you'll have this
adorable little quilt top that we
literally made so fast I mean look how
easy that was right I hope you felt like
it was easy alright what do you think
let me know in the comment section down
below what you think this video I'm so
excited for you guys let me know how
it's going if you're a beginner quilter
let me know if you have any questions
did I leave something out are you unsure
about something I would love to know and
love to be able to help you out so leave
comments down below all of the fabric
that I use different resources great
blog post that might be helpful all that
can be found in the description box
below the video so this is gonna be
video number one I will also once those
videos come out I will have down below
linked videos two three and four for
your basting quilting and binding so all
of that will be available for you guys
as well so stay tuned for video number
two and let me know how your first quilt
goes tag me on social media send me
photos I love to see what you all are
working on and I love to see how you
take my projects and make them your own
like I want to see what charm pack did
you pick out what was speaking to you at
the fabric store or on those photos as
you were looking at them online thanks
so much for watching I'll see you in the
next video bye